[Music]
Terry really great to sit down and talk
on camera so just a little bit of
background I understand that you've been
involved in the integral community for
many years you've been thinking deeply
about some of the same topics that we've
been covering on the channel and you've
also been watching quite a lot of the
stuff we've been putting out and what I
really like is that it seems that we're
the conversation has been evolving ever
since it started with Jordan Peterson
and some of the other thinkers and it's
kind of becoming a little bit more
self-aware that and I'm really
interested in your background and what
you you're interested in and keen to add
to the conversation and where we might
go in this this conversation today great
well there are a number of things that
you've been surfacing recently that are
taking us into another territory in your
conversations with daniel martin berger
and jordan Greenhalgh and others you're
facing the existential risk very
directly you're also bringing in
integral perspectives but you're staying
connected to the psychic depth that was
present in your original work with
Jordan Peterson and all of that is
beginning to constellation that's
emergent you're more curious about what
you don't know then you are interested
to rehash all the implications of what's
already been clarified and that's
absolutely essential because the
existential risk is more immediate and
more crucial that most people are able
to countenance you know and I want to
just sort of put a little flag in in
that now because one of the biggest
tensions that I can feel in the audience
and in in the general culture I think
it's a big rift within but the
intellectual darkweb constellation that
we've talked a bit about is this idea of
existential risk and where we are at as
a society because in some ways we're
certainly in one of the best my things
are as good as they've been you've got
the Steven Pinker's of this world saying
look at and they're right exactly so how
do we hold that complexity of
ever-increasing metrics in many many
different areas
at the same time this wide sense that a
lot of us have and especially sort of
some of the most the people who've
engaged with this the most and some of
the most profound thinkers that I've
encountered who also have this sense
that we're in a self terminating system
through exponential tech that is
becoming ever more fragile and the risks
of multiplying how do we hold both of
those things you just said that we're
right we are in the best of all worlds
in human history at the same time as we
have this sort of sense that there's
something not right right and there's
something even better than the fact that
we're in the best moment in human
history there's the fact that we have
accessed all the wisdom traditions of
mankind at once and we're in
conversation they are in conversation
with one another and with the methods of
modern science in a self-critical
examination that is liberating us to
radical and profound wisdom intuitions
which wake us up to the fact that if
we're really unclouded and awaked any
moment it's infinitely deep profound and
beautiful and gratitude and amazement or
our best relationship to every reality
so all of that is even better than the
fact things are better than they ever
were before but we have to have the
cognitive complexity to walk down the
street and chew gum at the same time and
it can be true that we are the luckiest
people who've ever lived that we have
access to more information wisdom
mobility pleasure innumerable advantages
and that this makes something new
possible and that it's a tremendously
exciting time to be alive and that we
are also alive at a time in which the
existential risk the unsustainability of
our current trajectory is becoming
obvious in in many different vectors
there are all kinds of natural world
issues we have an ecological dilemma
that is far wider and more complex than
just climate change
but our crisis isn't limited to the
ecological dimension we have crises in
culture and society that are undermining
our ability to make collective decisions
with any degree of wisdom and those in
some sense are more fundamental we also
have the arising of an attention economy
that's dumbing us down with a race to
the bottom of the brainstem in which
exponential tech has exceeded human
weakness in which we're reverse
engineering our nervous systems to turn
us into machines of destructive
consumption and where none of us able to
account for all of these things
adequately we're facing questions and
challenges that no analysis is equal to
we need to figure much more out about
all this the attempt to understand
better is crucial and I think that's
where we're actually leading that's our
our although we are facing questions for
which we don't have adequate answers we
are advancing rapidly in our ability to
understand where we are on the other
hand mere understanding isn't enough we
have to become different our very way of
being as being asked to shift not just
our lifestyles but even our not just in
not even just our values but there are
profound deepenings and shiftings
maturation of our humanity that are
alive in the domain of feeling and care
and if we're to actually achieve not
anti rival risk dynamics in our social
relations this is a demand for our
spiritual growth we can say but it's
also a growth of say friendship growth
of our ability to cooperate and we tend
not to drop into the the level of wonder
and amazement and presence and
vulnerability that are appropriate
you know I'm alive in a time when what
happens in my lifetime might very well
be determinative as to the future human
friendly or various kinds of animal
friendly conditions on the plane
in which the great-grandchildren of
human beings and the
great-great-great-great of almost every
other species not not every but many
many other species might hang in the
balance and I'm living a middle-class
lifestyle that's contributing to many of
the destructive vectors that are at play
so it takes a lot of human maturity to
be with this moral you know what could
have more moral force than our impact on
the whole future of life and yet if we
take that seriously we tend to get
contracted and panicked and upset and
lose track of the inherent happiness
that is the very nature of our sanity so
we're asked to grow and that being with
that request to grow breaks our conceit
of knowledge my my comfort in being
smart and figuring things out and being
excited about what's next rest in a
place where I'm not quite as self
questioning as is necessary so there's a
kind of vulnerability and the very rich
human dimensions they're really needing
to become primary in the conversation
now and yeah there's this there's this
tension and we've talked about this
before we started filming of the
intellectual understanding and the
system's understanding that we need to
kind of make sense of the world and also
but this sense that that we have as
people who've done been very familiar
with kind of different kinds of
spiritual practice but that's not enough
that actually there's another dimension
that's needed as well and it's quite
that's a synthesis that I don't see
quite coming to fruition yet but I think
we're where we're in this this is part
of the conversation that I think rebel
wisdom is trying to have in particular
is what are the different pieces that we
need to bring together so I'm interested
and you you've also talked about kind of
this conversation is becoming a bit more
self-aware and it's it certainly seems
to have a direction to it what do you
think where do you think it's at and
where do you think it needs to go well
one of the things that I appreciate most
about what you've done is that you have
continued to be curious and stay as I
said you have stayed interest more
interested in what
is emerging and what is new than simply
tracking the implications of what's
already obvious which is absolutely
crucial because where things are moving
very very fast and emergence is the name
of the game I think if you deeply
consider all of the data you come to the
conclusion that we are caught in a
dynamic that's going to require
nonlinear social transformation and that
that social transformation is going to
depend on profound maturity it's
probably only going to be achievable at
first in social experiment subcultures
places where a whole new set of
agreements can be established and
reinforced among limited numbers of
people so that they can achieve new
efficiencies can we unpack that with
nonlinear social what did you say
nonlinear social transformation
transformation can be unpack that
because that's as well it's it's
essentially if we if we reckon honestly
and courageously with intellectual
honesty and moral clarity we have to
recognize that all of us are living
lives that are right now actively
destroying the very life-support systems
that we are dependent on and that the
future is depended on and we have a
moral dilemma in relationship to our
great grandchildren's generations and
the future of life on the planet and
that is shocking and difficult it
disarms pretty much everything all the
good work you are doing that might
ripple out into posterity all your
family and kids and grandkids everything
you love everything you value may no
longer be viable all the things that
give our lives meaning may be challenged
this is a hyper object it's too big to
look at it's too big to reckon with even
emotionally or spiritually it's
overwhelming everyone I know who has
actually faced this not just in an
abstract mental way but in a felt and
embodied way has gone through
more than one dark nights of the soul
because this is essentially just too
horrible to contemplate it's a terrible
truth beyond our our knowing and it
doesn't contradict the wonderful truths
that are also simultaneously real and
what it is to be with what tends to
contract us and a fundamental trust of
being trust of life that is the essence
of sanity is a agha you might say of
human maturation that operates not just
in the domain of our understanding but
of our feeling and of our embodiment so
I think that the conversation that has
been emergent in honourable wisdom is
now cresting to a place where you're
able to contend with deeper paradoxes
than ever before and the transformation
of the focus from merely the advancement
of knowledge and understanding to the
actual experiments with new levels of
maturity and ways of being new kinds of
friendship and cooperation non-rival
risk dynamics what what is it to really
create them and that's not something
that we can simply understand abstractly
through game theory as brilliantly as
Daniels Markman Berger is able to
articulate those things he's a wonderful
thought leader and yet the the shift in
our ways of being in the heart-to-heart
conversations that it takes for us to
establish a different way of being
related to one another these are the
edge and I think that you're going to be
going into those places where the
conversation isn't just about
understanding but about practice where
the conversation isn't only about the we
have to objectify things in order to see
them clearly this is the essence of debt
of Robert Keegan's developmental theory
we make subject object but that
objectification of our own way of being
can also become a limitation when we are
self objectified we're remove
from full feeling presence in our own
experience and we're in a challenge now
to our feeling like the pre trans
fallacy in integral theory there's a
kind of way of being embedded in feeling
that we need to transcend we need to get
beyond our reactivity and our
unconscious feeling natures but then we
have to return to a capacity to feel
more deeply that to love to notice to
use our total intelligence which is
centered in the brain in many respects
primarily but there are also centers of
intelligence in that are studied in
neuro cardiology at the heart and neuro
enter ology of the God the whole sensing
organism is needed and we have hyper
specialized and fragmented to the point
that almost all of our conversations are
partial and and that's ok because that's
our context of course we're going to
come with partial perspectives but a
compassionate and curious conversation
opens into inquiring beyond those limits
and that epistemic humility and the
availability that that opens up the
vulnerability and curiosity to learn
from one another
shifts the whole nature of the
conversation a kind of shared inquiry
that really our lives depend on and in
many ways has to open up and all along
that way we're gonna have to
course-correct even right now as I speak
with you I notice I'm excited I want to
get these ideas out my energies gone up
a little higher in my body there's a
relaxation into this trust of being that
wouldn't be a bad thing for me to be
reminded of there's a always little of
course Corrections that every one of us
would do well to make in every moment so
if this conversation is to be emergent I
want
be willing to shift and if I have the
kind of access to you that allows me to
help you shift so that virtuous cycles
of mutual help become the nature of our
ways of interaction so that the vicious
cycles the races to the bottom that are
on every side are actually able to be
interrupted in active time these are new
kinds of relationships for us to have
with one another and so this
conversation among practitioners in
which we inquire into our richest
possibilities that's I think the place
that your consideration will naturally
take itself if you pursue it with rigor
and integrity and and humility so it's
obviously the rebel wisdom the channel
sort of originated from the interest in
Jordan Peterson and the interest in the
phenomenon of Jordan Peterson as much as
the the message of Jordan Peters and of
course the two things are deeply
intertwined and I'm hugely impressed
with this thinking as well I wouldn't
dismiss that and then what I what I
sensed with him was there was a very
almost a theory of everything a kind of
integral theory of everything which both
of us admit familiar with from Ken
Wilbur's work and interested in the sort
of the dialogue between these two very
very singular and very interesting
visions of trying to bring lots of
different wisdom traditions together and
lots of different historical traditions
obviously Jordan Peterson mainly focused
on the mythopoetic the mythic tradition
and the Christian tradition and can
probably a bit more interested in the
Eastern traditions of of wisdom and
Buddhism and bringing those together and
obviously you've been in you've been
involved in the integral community for
many years I'd really love to get your
take on on those two different visions
where they interact maybe where they
where you see the the shortcomings or
where they don't where they don't
coincide but there's certainly a very
interesting dialogue to be had between
those two really amazing thinkers and
amazing perspectives well my own
background of spiritual practice is what
I call a transcendental spirituality
non-dual spirituality which is pretty
much Ken's
history as well and this really has to
do with waking up from false forms of
separation false divisions waking up
beyond the self and other the story of
separation waking into the ineffable
mystery many many false divisions
following away and us arriving at the
level of being in a full liberation of
awareness and feeling it the intuition
of ourselves is not separate from all
things and this is I think the the
senior you might you might call it
senior in a certain sense because the
highest realizations of the great
mystical traditions are all arriving at
that understanding and that has a
certain kind of practice or sadhana and
it's a universal sudden we all whatever
our particular form of expression wake
up to the same undifferentiated
suchness and mystery and beingness and
love and freedom and joy and all the
rest that's it's a universal path but
we're also each unique individuals and
the uniqueness of each individual is
also a mystical path and that's more
than mythopoetic path it's soul work and
that soul work has to do with
understanding our well actually not
understanding so much it has to do with
dropping to a deeper level of attention
we're in the different kind of
information becomes available some of
the most important decisions that every
human being makes in their lives are
very particular to you which college do
you go to do you marry that sweetheart
or do you divorce at a certain point in
a stuck relationship do you move to a
certain town do you form this
partnership or that those are very
particular decisions and
they do need to be informed by our
deepest wisdom and our deepest wisdom is
not going to be found in the universal
mystery the universal mystery loves you
and helps you be clearer and maybe you
enter into that decision with a kind of
spaciousness of attention that is of a
different character but it doesn't give
you any particular data about which way
to go that really comes from in the
traditions the this transcendental form
of things would be associated with the
causal and non dual the mythopoetic
relates to the subtle and the subtle or
soul levels are where all kinds of very
specific information can be available
where we can be guided by deeper subtler
knowings and that are much more embodied
that subtle realm has a lot to do with
shamanism journeys the mysticism of the
natural world sometimes there are you
know people have all kinds of ways of
interacting totem animals spirit
visitations indigenous wisdom is key to
this myth of poetic love the
storytellers and there's a whole world
of beautiful and important spirituality
there and it takes the soul and the
journey in time as its foundations
whereas the transcendental spiritual
path wakes you up to the emptiness of
self the emptiness of time you transcend
all that to exclusively always try to
transcend that ends up almost always
with certain kinds of bypassing to just
be focused on the soul work and the
mythopoetic path almost always ends up
in a kind of ego 'ti because I I can do
that work and discover my purpose and
have my fulfilling work and my soulmate
and all kinds of things that are
peculiar to my own path and and that
easily slip over into self fulfilling
and and and an imagination that that
self is ultimately real you can
do that deep soul work and if your soul
realizes its purpose fully these two
paths become a single you know you might
say an enchanted but but but in another
way a very clear and open available
human being and within that I think
there's an a release of feeling of every
kind of feeling there's a an opening of
360 degree feeling an ability to feel
all the things that enter wait to to
horrible to feel the the degree of
contradiction that we are in I am Alive
in a world in which my very lifestyle is
part of what it is that is killing the
future of everything I love that's too
horrible to feel and there is so much
suffering in the world human and
non-human it's very hard to allow
ourselves to really feelingly in an
embodied way be actually related to that
we're almost all of us numbed out in
relation to all that and that has us
there in our heads and it has us
figuring things out and it has us having
arrogant conversations that aren't
really deeply feelingly related to
what's really going on on the other hand
the that embodied engagement easily
slips into the inherent you might call
it a centricity the targeting mechanism
of the self becomes the conceit through
which everything is seen and therefore
we're essentially selfish we'll never
through the mythopoetic path alone we
will never get beyond rival risk
dynamics we actually have to be changed
in a way that requires the transcendent
spirituality so we're being asked really
for an enormous leap of personal
maturation and it has to express itself
it's not only do I have to mature in all
those ways but I have to find other
people who are close enough to the
maturation I'm going through that I can
engage with them in a way where we
become a different kind of collective
where friendship becomes something
different community and corporation
become something different we're
genuinely non-rival risk dynamics come
into being that enable cooperation to
out-compete competition because that is
in a way the design spec of any kind of
healthy social movement scaling in a
time when that's absolutely critical
because there's this there's a kind of
paradox if we take Jordan Peterson as
the kind of his the focus on the
individual in Jordan Peterson like I see
Jordan Peterson as necessary may be
essential but not sufficient like what
he's bringing this focus on the
individual this focus on being really
clear about the impact of your words
being really self-critical about the way
that your own your own truth and
orienting yourself by that is absolutely
essential and in some ways you can't
bypass that to go to cooperation or
collaboration without without
continually coming back to that
individual perspective but it is it is
insufficient and I see a lot of people
who criticize Jordan Peterson for for
for that focus on the individual until
the woman is characterizing him as a
kind of Ain Rand cut type figure than
any kind of collaboration any kind of
collective action is is undesired or
rough want of a better word for me that
misses the point because we have to go
through that that to be able and in some
sense if we go through enough into our
own our own cell we need to have gone
through our own stuff to the point where
we actually do recognize ourselves in
the other that there is this sense of we
are if you want to take a sort of deep
Taoist or Buddhist perspective we are
the same being looking out through
through other eyes but the thing that's
preventing us from seeing that is our
own personal history our own personal
stuff our own personal conditioning and
our sense of separation that then leads
us to those rivalries dynamics of trying
to get ahead at the cost of it of other
people
so it's only through that that deep
inner work and focus on the individual
we can come to a genuine collective
connection and collaboration that is not
going to be undermined by all of that
unresolved stuff if that I I kind of
agree what I would argue is everything
is necessary to everything else a
holistic transformation is obliged upon
us the outer work can't wait
we can't wait in the United States we
can't wait to come together to some
degree to defeat Trump even with people
who lack many of the essential
understandings that are most important
to us we still have to find our way into
different levels of communion with other
people and authentic relating in a new
way we have to and we have to do the
personal work I often will abbreviate
the nature of an integral practice as
consisting of the inner work the outer
work and the inter interpersonal work
and that outer work in a way has two
dimensions like the four quadrants would
imply and that there's behavior change
and then there systems change and both
are crucial so people who are
experimenting with real ocol ization who
are paying attention to the wisdom of
indigenous people who are focused on the
inescapability of our ecological origins
people in my book I described three
groups the ecologists the innovators and
the evolutionary's as each of them
holding essential pieces of the human
future and being in serious
conversations about them well if we
don't do all that work at once we're not
getting where we want to go so I agree
with you
Jordan Peterson is pointing us to
something really essential but I think
he's also pointing us away from
something else that's also essential it
is absolutely true that we're not going
to fulfill our collective actions in
anything like the way we need to unless
we ourselves are transformed but it's
also true that there are collective
actions we have to take right away
before we're transformed so the emphasis
of one essential piece of reality at the
expense of another is endemic in so many
of our conversations so I think that the
inquiry are engaging at rebel wisdom
will mature more and more as you are
sifting out how to hold multiple
essential truths that seem to be in
tension with one another and then
holding them the act that the practice
of holding them as individuals and in
relation to one another I think this is
the the leading edge of where your
consideration is going to lead yeah and
I want to address one of those
conflicting truths or perspectives which
is talked about if we're going to use
integral term and all you can talk about
green-green as a person as a
relativistic postmodern perspective that
obviously Jordan Peterson has a very
strong antipathy to and I think Ken and
the interview that I did with him as
well said that if he has shadow material
that's also located in this antipathy to
green and I wanted to and I know that
you're much more sympathetic toward to
the green purse perspective and I wanted
to kind of ask you to explore that a
little bit what do you think we're
missing if we're throwing out you I
guess you'd say that we're throwing out
the baby with the bathwater if we
redirect green can you explain what that
means like unpack what green is for
people it may be a lot so familiar with
the term and then say then maybe talk
about what how we how we integrate it
from your perspective well you know we
went from thinking that the truth was in
the Bible and what the king and the Pope
said in the traditional era to using the
methods of science and observation and
the magic of the free market and the
modern time to beginning to recognize
that whoever dies with the most toys
wins only a soulless game and that deep
sensitivity to our interiors and to the
hidden structures that can
work to suppress and distort and hurt
and oppress disadvantaged groups people
of color or women LGBTQ people and so
forth this is the the postmodern but
postmodern is the least mature of these
broadly you know there are large
populations occupying primarily
traditional or modern or postmodern
values and those in the postmodern are
the least fully developed and you can
have people of any level of personal
cognitive complexity and ability
adopting the values and ideas of any of
these values so the ones that are
adopting postmodern values very often
are doing so in a rather narrow way with
belief motivating them and because so
adopting it as an ideology rather than
as a value system perhaps might be a way
of well they're there perhaps they don't
have necessarily the cognitive
complexity or personal maturity to have
arrived at this very nuanced middle
vision logic is the term for the kind of
cognitive complexity required at the
postmodern level and very often people
are adopting those values because
they're kind of cool you know in the
urban centers with very limited lacked
action logics and so they approach it in
a way that is full of us them dynamics
and and and limited views and you have
this increase in sensitivity and many
people are really experiencing that
increase in sensitivity and is the
sensitive self comes online in this
postmodern level but that sensitivity
can function destructively when we say
oh well this hurts my feelings and we
shouldn't let anybody have a talk here
at my college that might offend my
feelings and we begin to shut down
dialogue and there's this mean green
phenomenon and I find that utterly
confounding and frustrating just like
Jorgen Peterson and Ken Wilber do but
the postmodern level of meaning making
is also the one that first begins to
grok
ecosystems and the necessity of living
in harmony with a bigger reality and is
less anthropocentric and actually able
to humble itself before its foundations
and and understand the deep deep truths
of Deep Ecology it deep ecology may be
held in a doctrinaire and problematic
way by some people but it is also
holding deep truths so in my view mature
integral expresses in what I call
radical integral ecology in which the
deep truths of deep ecology and the
profound truths of integral are
simultaneously held and that means
getting beyond our allergies to
post-modernism so that these either/or
dynamics are nuked we we always have to
reject what we outgrow at first and we
are all in a moment in which there are
environments in which really ugly
useless postmodern rigidities get
inflicted upon us where men have no
voice in the conversation around gender
where anybody who admits to having some
you know every one of us has evolved
through hundreds of years hundreds of
thousands of years in hunter-gatherer
bands or who was in my clan and who was
in the other clan was absolutely
essential and implicit bias racial bias
exists everywhere and therefore
everybody in that sense is a little bit
racist
and yet racism has become such a moral
condemnation that the fact that any
anybody admits this is sort of taboo and
and and so if you're white and male and
my age you're supposed to be the last to
speak or maybe you shouldn't speak at
all but complexities of what goes on
it's it's you know it's garbage it's a
mess on the other hand the care there is
care in that critique that the care is
being exercised in a clumsy and violent
and destructive way but there's still
something
heard about that matters so postmodern
values do not need to be discarded
they're absolutely essential to our
maturation and especially at a time when
we're in an existential crisis many of
the of whose most significant dimensions
are ecological that the postmodern
worldview which is the basis for the
broad appreciation for our ecological
origins in nature is you know to be
fighting with that is that's the
elephant in the room so there's a
problem I think in the intellectual dark
web in integral circles at the leading
edge of culture when we notice the
limitations of post-modernism in such a
way that we lose touch with our own
moral obligation to be champions of a
new reunification that especially
includes we're going to we have to
repair in our lives in a way that is
actually sustainable on this planet
Earth and that is such an enormous
transition that reap a turning of our
lives that a deep sacred appreciation
for the earth for what is most basic for
what is most fundamental is essential to
our sanity and if our conversation can't
become stronger in that dimension we're
lost I think both you and I from our
background in history have some sense
that it's not just an intellectual I'm
gonna start again I think we both have
some sense from our kind of background
and history that a lot of the the people
addressing these issues at the moment
are coming from a very intellectual
level and there's a sense of the systems
thinkers and there's there's a there's
an abandonment or there's not an
understanding of the the more embodied
nature of the transformation that we
need to go through and I think more and
more people are kind of sensing that but
I think key to that has to be some kind
of techniques or practice or
and yes some some way of interacting
with our own in estates and maybe
processing and maybe what what's your
attitude to practice and how important
do you think that is for for the
transition that we're looking at
practice is at the center of my Dharma
because in a sense practice is living
intentionally it's intentionally
cultivating what is best in ourselves or
we can practice together practice isn't
only individual it can be collective you
give some examples of practice just so
we can kind of ground that well sure
practices include meditation conscious
exercise yoga Qigong psychotherapy
medicine journeys they also it also
includes just physical strengthening gym
anything that we do any repeated
activity that changes us and it
cultivates new qualities we think we can
call a practice and as we really deepen
into an integral full understanding of
what practice is we realized that just
putting your time in on the cushion is
not enough that you have to cultivate a
body mind that is capable of conducting
more energy and consciousness that it
that it's a whole being
multi-dimensional matter and that every
moment of life involves choices where we
fall unconsciously into patterns by
tendency and where we can make different
and better choices so that really all of
life is practice if it's rightly
understood and in a moment in which we
are all shaped to a very strong momentum
of human culture that's growth based and
competition based and those patterns are
tending to become self terminating we're
asked to go through a collective
transformation and that transformation
ideally would involve us bringing our
intentions together in a whole different
way so collective practice is also
obligatory and the conversation among
practitioners might go something
like gosh I'm feeling really great
because my consciousness is opening up
in this way and this and that has
changed in some of my relationships and
man I feel like I'm in a whole new level
of my life right now my friend might
respond yeah but you know you're a
little inflated in a certain way and
that enthusiasm almost bowls me over I'm
not sure there's room for you to really
hear and feel me and take me in you seem
so full of your own new insight and I
might then learn from that and shift and
take that person into account in a
better way or in another moment I might
share the place where I feel like I'm up
against something and my good
practitioner friend might share not just
you know we tend to tell our own stories
to one another very very often we don't
engage real conversations we're in a
moment now culturally where we actually
have to hear listen take in one another
care enough to actually engage that
other and most human conversations are
not even close to that level currently
so we're cultivating a different kind of
fellowship and friendship as well so the
conversation among practitioners might
also then be one in which we really seek
to get each other this is something like
circling and authentic communication but
certainly an authentic communication
rarely take as their prompt our
collective evolutionary imperative the
fact that everything has to change we're
mostly preoccupied with healing and
succeeding within the existing system
not acknowledging that it too has to
change so the profundity of the
challenge that we're all living under
tends not to be surfaced in a way that
brings us together in a
your way I think those are frontiers
that are the frontier of practice is an
integration of the inner work it or work
the outer work behavior change systems
change becoming effective change agents
through social entrepreneurship and
sometimes protest and a whole variety of
things everybody is holding a piece of
the truth very often they're inflicting
limitations on others and they're
arrogant but with enough epistemic
humility we can include others and we're
gonna have to because there's no way
through this and in in this country in
the United States
I need the Trump voters I'm not gonna
succeed even if I get all the folks who
want to help me vote out Trump which I'd
love to do that those that isn't enough
we're not going forward as a society
unless we find our commonality at a
broader level and so a kind of
compassion and respect for people who
are getting a lot of things wrong is
essential to our life of practice so
practice is in a moment where it itself
must evolve our very best versions of
practice are a beginning point not an
end point so the the the profundity of
the sacred that which you actually bow
down before this is holy this is greater
than me and and we can respond both to
the ineffable mystery of existence with
that kind of heartfelt gratitude and
submission and we can also respond to
the living earth that way those are
different kinds of sanctity one of them
is theoretically at the top of the
evolutionary sequence and what is the
foundation but this Universal
appreciation of the sacred as both the
ground and the destiny of our life of
practice creates a context in which the
heart can
respond the intelligent one with the
executive function who's steering the
ship has better information to work with
on the basis of all this but we're not
gonna get there if the only people who
can do what's necessary are the ones
with massive levels of intellectual
sophistication part of what we're
looking for is the simplicity on the
other side of that complexity which is a
different way of being human that we can
live in common with many different kinds
of human beings and when we're seeing
the essential sacred divine nature you
might say of every human soul even as
we're looking through the illusion of
selfhood and discovering another way of
being human all together that none of us
can see yet
I just want to pick up on the point you
made about Trump and because my sense is
that Trump won't be voted out or the we
won't see a shift there until the
lessons of Trump are learned and I for
me the lessons of Trump are that the
liberal classes created this in somewhat
the shadow of the liberal class has
created this in some way with this sense
of a tribalism that didn't want to admit
that it was a tribalism we're so liberal
we're so inclusive apart from the
deplorable z' and the Trump was a
reaction to that and I don't see I when
we're talking about practice and we're
talking about kind of seeing a deeper
connectedness that's the the issue that
I see is the big problem is this is
until we learn the lessons of Trump and
I don't see real really any signs of
that amongst the sort of certainly the
Democrats certainly the sort of the
wider liberal classes do you agree with
that diagnosis partially I I do think
that there is so let me tell you where I
don't disagree first where I disagree
first there's a great deal of corruption
right now in the Republican Party and
there are there
we are under pressure we are under
stress and under stress dysfunction
comes forward and there's a fair amount
of psychopathy in every society and that
psychopathy has concentrated and become
pretty you know very significant
majority of it is concentrated on the
right in supporting the Republican Party
and so there is something that simply
has to be resisted so I'm sympathetic
with aspects of the left side of the
polarization there is there are two
things I absolutely am against
psychopathy and cynicism my politics are
anti psychopathic and anti cynical there
there are there are all kinds of
dysfunctions operative on the left but
what I see in maybe a typical Democratic
candidate like Cory Booker is something
a heck of a lot more healthy so I'm I'm
not alarmed by Cory Booker in anything
like the way I'm alarmed by what I see
in Donald Trump and therefore I do think
that there is a little bit of a good guy
bad guy dynamic at work there and I'm
happy to be with the Democrats in that
particular polar polarity because I
think it's important however I think
that the demonization of racism and the
the superiority that successful coastal
elites feel to the Trump voters in
flyover country are definitely a big
part of what has created the Trump
phenomenon and I didn't I agree with you
that there's not nearly enough self
awareness about those limitations I
think a different level of compassion
and respect is necessary but very often
you know the people who are trying to
convene trans partisan conversations
find that it's a lot easier to get
people on the Left who want to have
those conversations than people on the
right and that's that's a sign of
something
and and it doesn't speak well to what's
on the right so in my view of things
they're they're kind of ought to be and
I hope there will be a powerful
repudiation of Trump in the next
election and I think that will open an
opportunity because the people who come
together to try to oppose him will have
some commonality out of which some of
these healthier expressions and some of
the important critiques of the excesses
of post-modernism can be surfaced and
maybe we can you know we have some
opportunities to coalesce aspects of the
International intergenerational movement
that you the human predicament requires
on the other hand the there there is
there's also a there's an availability
among people who are involved in their
attention to their sensitivities if
they're spoken to in terms of what they
can feel so although there are plenty of
whatever I don't Muslim women of color
who are lesbians I know somebody in the
most disadvantaged group who ought to
speak first in the left-wing meeting
that you know all only marginalized
voices ought to be heard first very
often that person might be so full of
self-righteousness and thinking they
know what's what and they just want to
talk and not listen but caught in the
right moment and in the right context
there's also a sensitivity to their own
lived and felt experience and therefore
a curiosity about the lived and felt
experience of people they haven't closed
their hearts to and if that can be
extended all the way eventually to white
men that we have a kind of access to
them and I think we also have access to
the Trump voters it's just that it takes
tremendous maturity and a kind of
unconditional loving appreciation that
we are not really ultimately separate to
look at somebody in that way and feel
them and speak to their what's best in
though trusting that that will
eventually find its way to surface is
really skillful communication and it
won't work with somebody who's
fundamentally committed to a
psychopathic or cynical orientation and
there are people on both left and right
that we're not going to be able to reach
but I think that this sense that our
heartfelt communications that draw us
into our commonality and wake us up to
the fact that we're in the same troubled
lifeboat together
that is our opportunity right now and
there that's going to make a lot
possible that's never been possible
before mmm like I guess I'd agree with a
lot of what you said the bit that didn't
scan for me and I know won't scan for a
lot of people is saying that people on
the left are more open to conversation
and people on the right I think there's
a certainly I mean something Eric
Weinstein talks about a lot Brett
Weinstein talks about a lot that
actually they found much more openness
to have discussions especially about hot
topics on among the center right and
they do among the left because those
conversations often shut down with
accusations of bigotry or whatever and
and that feels true to me like there's
certain things that can be discussed in
the media and in academia I think that
that uh that the force of censorship I
do feel is coming more from the left and
from the right so I wonder whether
actually I agree with you I think I was
talking more about my own experience
with individuals there are environments
particularly the academies and certain
activist circles in the urban centers
where the left is very closed and and
and just suppressive that's why it's
been from the left that we've seen so
many attacks on free speech but that
doesn't not nonetheless we I I think
have an opportunity to scale the
beginnings
the kind of movement we want to see in
many areas of culture which are you know
some of them very important ones are on
the center-right but I'd say the larger
population is more toward the left
although there are elements the left
that are going to fight it to the man
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon
you